A Guide to the E.C. Stakman Papers FA052
Rockefeller Archive Center
E.C. Stakman papers
1911-1969
Rockefeller Archive Center
Stakman, E. C. (Elvin Charles), 1885-1979
Rockefeller Foundation
FA052
0.95 Cubic Feet 3 letter document cases
Biographical / Historical
Plant pathologist, educator, and humanitarian, Elvin Charles Stakman was one of the most important figures in agricultural science during the first half of the twentieth century. He was born on May 17, 1885, at Algoma, Wisconsin, and received his undergraduate (1906) and Ph.D. degrees (1913) from the University of Minnesota. From 1909 until 1953 he was a member of the faculty of that university, retiring with the rank of Distinguished Professor.
Dr. Stakman's principal scientific fame came from his studies of wheat stem rusts. He discovered that this crop disease was not a single stable entity but a fungus that evolved into new strains which could infect plants resistant to its earlier forms. Among the scientists who collaborated in his efforts to control this blight and develop new rust-resistant strains of wheat were Norman Borlaug, who won a Nobel Prize for his work, and J. George Harrar, later president of The Rockefeller Foundation. Both were graduate students of Dr. Stakman.
Dr. Stakman played a major role in the Rockefeller Foundation's efforts to increase food production in developing countries. This grew out of an assignment in the 1940s on behalf of the Foundation to undertake an examination of agricultural productivity in Mexico. His recommendation that the Foundation initiate a major program to improve crop yields in developing countries led to the Foundation's early involvement in the so-called "Green Revolution."
After his retirement from the University of Minnesota in 1953, Dr. Stakman worked as a consultant for The Rockefeller Foundation, a post he retained until his death. He also accepted a series of visiting professorships at universities in the United States, Mexico, and India during this period.
Dr. Stakman married Louise Jensen, a member of the University of Minnesota faculty, on September 6, 1917. She predeceased him. Dr. Stakman died in St. Paul, Minnesota, on January 22, 1979.
Scope and Contents
The E. C. Stakman Papers contain few items of a personal nature. Consisting of clippings, correspondence, program notes listing Dr. Stakman as a speaker, reprints, and speeches (mostly testimonials to Dr. Stakman), the papers reflect only the public side of his career. Over three-quarters of this collection consists of reprints. Most of the correspondence here is incoming rather than from the hand of Dr. Stakman. Only a few items reflect his activities on behalf of The Rockefeller Foundation.
Arrangement
The E. C. Stakman Papers are arranged alphabetically by document type: clippings, correspondence, program notes and news releases, reprints, and speeches.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
E. C. Stakman donated his papers to The Rockefeller Foundation between November 1967 and April 1971.
File Plan
Former Classification: IV 2A 35
Agriculture
- Clippings, 1927-1958 and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1919, 1932-1954 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Program Notes and News Releases, 1939-1967 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Reprints, 1911-1929 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Reprints, 1911-1929 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Reprints, 1911-1929 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Reprints, 1911-1929 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Reprints, 1930-1960 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Reprints, 1930-1960 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Reprints, 1930-1960 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Reprints, 1930-1960 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Reprints, 1930-1960 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Reprints, 1961-1969 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Speeches, 1948-1965 (Box 3, Folder 14)